<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The dovvnefall of Shebna together with an application to the bloudie Gowrie of Scotland. As it was deliuered in two seuerall sermons of that occasion, in S. Maries Church in Oxford. And now published for a warning to all ill-affected Ogiluiests: vt quorum exitus perhorrescunt, eorum facta non imitentur. By I.S.</title>
            <author>Singleton, Isaac, b. 1582 or 3.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 102 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12264</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22574</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117442</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852655</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852655</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17988</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12264)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17988)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1034:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The dovvnefall of Shebna together with an application to the bloudie Gowrie of Scotland. As it was deliuered in two seuerall sermons of that occasion, in S. Maries Church in Oxford. And now published for a warning to all ill-affected Ogiluiests: vt quorum exitus perhorrescunt, eorum facta non imitentur. By I.S.</title>
                  <author>Singleton, Isaac, b. 1582 or 3.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 42, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [at Eliot's Court Press] for Iohn Bill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Isaac Singleton.</note>
                  <note>Identification of printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gowrie Conspiracy, 1600 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17988:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17988:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>DOVVNEFALL OF SHEBNA: <hi>Together with</hi> AN APPLICATION to the bloudie GOWRIE of SCOTLAND.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As it was deliuered in two ſeuerall Sermons</hi> of that occaſion, in S. MARIES Church <hi>IN OXFORD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now publiſhed for a warning to all ill-affected OGILVIESTS: <hi>Vt quorum exitus perhorreſcunt, e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> facta non imiten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY <hi>J. S.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 37.28.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Lord loueth Iudgement, and forſaketh not his Saints. They ſhall be preſerued for euermore: but the ſeed of the wicked ſhall be cut off.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON Printed for <hi>John Bill.</hi> 1615.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17988:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17988:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT Reuerend Father in God, my very eſpeciall good Lord and Patron, IOHN KING, <hi>Biſhop of London, J. S.</hi> Wiſheth all true happineſſe in CHRIST IESVS.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Lordſhip,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue (according to the receiued cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie) made bold to recommend this Treatiſe of <hi>SHEBNA his Downefall</hi> to your patronage, as a teſtimonie of mine vnfained thankfulneſſe for your many fauours and beneficence. In accepting whereof, I humbly pray you to imitate the goodneſſe of Almightie God, who, as a learned Father ſaith, <hi>Coronat voluntatem, vbi non inuenit facultatem.</hi> For otherwiſe had not I this ſtrong confidence, I ſo well vnderſtand mine owne diſabilitie, and
<pb facs="tcp:17988:3"/>take ſo little pleaſure in proclaiming the ſame, as that this liuely repreſentation of my many defects had neuer come to your Lordſhips view, much leſſe patronage. I know it needs a Patron; I dare not truſt mine owne eie: the obiect is too neere to be well diſcerned. And I cannot but remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in this bookiſh age the complaint of <hi>Andromache.</hi> Ω <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">Eurip. An. drom.</note> O opinion, opinion: thou haſt made many to thinke well of themſelues, who were nothing indeed. Right Reuerend; let it haue your countenance, and as for others, if any man know more concerning the Subiect heere han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled, either <hi>Shebna,</hi> or <hi>Gowrie,</hi> my paines may ſerue to ſtirre vp in him a deſire to profit more, that ſo what he knoweth, <hi>ſciat &amp; alter.</hi> If any know leſſe, I truſt he will rather thanke me, then cenſure me. There is none I aſſure my ſelfe ſo rigid and deuoid of ingenuitie, that will denie <hi>exiguis hunc addere rebus honorem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the Lord that made heauen and earth <hi>bleſſe you out of Sion:</hi> the Lord guide and proſper you in all your waies: the Lord eſtabliſh your houſe and familie, that you may ſee your childrens children, and an happy addition of many good and comfortable daies in this life, and this life ended, eternall happineſſe in the kingdome of heauen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips Chaplaine in all humble dutie and ſeruice to be commanded, ISAAC SINGLETON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17988:3"/>
            <head>THE DOWNEFALL OF SHEBNA.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ISAY 22.15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Goe get thee vnto this Treaſurer euen vnto Shebna, which is ouer the houſe, and ſay.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough it be true that the Iudge of all the world muſt needs do right<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 18.25.</note>, and that hee who is of infinite maieſtie, power, and iuſtice, can do no leſſe then auenge himſelfe of ſinne and ſinfull men; yet ſuch is his patience and longanimitie, that now and then, as the wiſe man ſaith, <hi>diſſimulat peccata hominum</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Wiſd. 7.</note>, he diſſembleth and ſeemeth not to ſee the ſinnes of men. And as <hi>S. Auſtin</hi> obſerueth, there is not alwaies <hi>apertio oculorum,</hi> when as this God ſeeth with the open eie, and takes apparant notice of the miſchieuous practiſes of euill doers; but ſometime <hi>opertio,</hi> when he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidereth (as I may ſo ſay) with the eie-lid, and appeares vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the wicked as one that ſleepes, and winkes at their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieties.</p>
            <p>Inſomuch that the crie of <hi>Sodome</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 18.25.</note> came vp to the very gates of heauen ere he came downe to them: the <hi>wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17988:4"/>of the Amorites</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">13.16.</note> was rotten ripe ere he began to launce; and the day of <hi>trouble and time</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Iſai. 22.15.</note> prefixt expired, ere he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded in iudgment with the Princes of <hi>Iuda.</hi> And <hi>Shebna</hi> in my text by his many impieties and wicked machinations euen turned his patience into fury ere he ſent our Prophet vnto him to threaten his ruine. Till at length the ſinnes of <hi>Shebna</hi> began to crie, and the meaſure of his iniquitie waxed full, and the day of his trouble came; and then when hee thought himſelfe moſt ſtrong, and flouriſhed like the bay tree<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal.</note>, when he dwelt in the cliffes of the rocke<note n="g" place="margin">Ier. 49.16.</note>, and kept the height of the hilles, and was (to vſe our Prophets words in the fiue and twentieth verſe<note n="h" place="margin">Iſai. 22.25.</note> of this Chapter) as a naile faſtned in a ſure place, loe, euen then comes a fearfull meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age and moſt direfull prediction of his vtter ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, <hi>Goe get thee vnto this Treaſurer, euen vnto Shebna which is ouer the houſe and ſay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which parcell of holy Writ may very well be intituled, <hi>The Downefull of Shebna. Occidit vna domus, ſed enim domus illa perire Digna fuit.</hi> For the better vnfolding wherof con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider with mee I beſeech you theſe three propoſals.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, <hi>What this Shebna was.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Secondly, <hi>What was his offence.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>And thirdly, <hi>How it was puniſhed.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>As touching the firſt, what this <hi>Shebna</hi> was; goe wee no further then to the title heere giuen him, and the bare ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification of the name it ſelfe, wee ſhall finde, that as was his name, ſo was hee: for the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which our Engliſh renders <hi>Treaſurer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Muſculus.</note> as <hi>Muſculus</hi> very well obſerueth, is not ſo much a name of office, as parentage: and he was called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Socuite,</hi> from the Citie wherein hee was borne. Now the Verbe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> either ſignifieth to impoueriſh; ſo that <hi>Shebna</hi> as it ſhould ſeeme, was one that was giuen to wrong and hurt others, and ſet light hy all ſuch as had not relation to him, and fauoured his proceedings: and therefore among his other vices, which doubtleſſe were many and great (as you ſhall heare anon) the holy Ghoſt<note n="i" place="margin">Iſa. 22.21.</note> in the one and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth verſe of this Chapter, plalnly ſpecifieth the malice and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17988:4"/>ſpleene which hee bare vnto good <hi>Eliachim;</hi> and to regret and gall him the more, it is recorded as a parcell of his pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, that whereas hee laboured to ſupplant <hi>Eliachim,</hi> and bring him into diſgrace with the Prince and State, <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>achim</hi> ſhould be aduanced, and that in <hi>Shebna</hi> roome: For <hi>with thy garments will I cloath him, and with thy girdle will I ſtrengthen him: thy power alſo will I commit into his hand, and he ſhall be a father of the Inhabitants of Ieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 22.21.</note> 
               <hi>and of the houſe of Iudah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or elſe it ſignifies to entertaine, to warme and cheriſh. In which ſenſe it is vſed the firſt of <hi>Kings,</hi> the firſt Chapter, and ſecond verſe,<note place="margin">1 Reg. 1.2.</note> where it is ſaid that the ſeruants of <hi>Dauid</hi> perceiuing a decay of nature, and that his vitall heat was well-nigh ſpent, they brought a young Virgin vnto him, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>&amp; ſit ei proficiens, foueat cum,</hi> let her che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh him. Which ſignification of the word if we will follow in this title, then wee may conceiue <hi>Shebna</hi> was a great fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and by his reuelling and banquetting and royall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment and other his more ſecret practiſes indeered the loues and affections of the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> and <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> but eſpecially of the falſe and hollow-hearted people and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall ſubiects of <hi>Ezechia</hi> vnto him, in ſuch ſort, as that all men ſtood in awe of him.</p>
            <p>Howſoeuer, certaine it is,<note place="margin">Tacitus hist. <hi>1.</hi> ſect. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> he was a man of ſpeciall regard and eminencie in the common wealth: For though hee were an Aegyptian borne and a meere ſtranger to the Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh nation, and a man who was beſides thoſe diſaduantages of birth and life: the one, being meane, baſe and obſcure, the other, lewd, wicked and vngodly, no way likely to riſe in ſo good and well ordered an eſtate, as this of Iudah.</p>
            <p>Yet had he by ſome ſuch vertues, as <hi>Tacitus</hi> mentioneth in <hi>Tigellinus, Luxurie</hi> and <hi>Crueltie,</hi> and ſuch other their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable companions, ſo humored the wicked King <hi>Ahaz,</hi> and by his fauour wrought himſelfe into ſuch place and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall imployment in the common wealth, as that <hi>Ezechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> though hee were a good and a pious Prince, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all queſtion made choiſe of his ſeruants thereafter, yet
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17988:5"/>hee not onely continued <hi>Shebna</hi> in that preſent greatneſſe, whereunto <hi>Ahaz</hi> had aduanced him: But ſeconded what <hi>Ahaz</hi> had begun, and followed <hi>Shebna</hi> with many an addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and freſh ſupply of future fauour and preferment. For whereas there are but two courſes, which Princes ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally take with ſuch as hold not correſpondence with them, either to diſgrace and caſheir them quite, or elſe to winne them by conferring fauors and honors vpon them: you haue many imbrace the former, and <hi>Dauid</hi> himſelfe though abuſed by a falſe and ſlandering fugitiue could hardly brooke <hi>Mephiboſheth:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 19.25.</note> 
               <hi>wherefore wenteſt not thou with me Mephiboſheth?</hi> Yet this good King tooke the faireſt and moſt charitable courſe, and heaped coales of fire vpon this wicked <hi>Shebna</hi> his head. And this will euidently appeare, if you will be pleaſed to take a view of the place which <hi>Shebna</hi> now held vnder <hi>Ezechiah,</hi> and of the great accompt which this good King made of him and of his ſeruice. For, to omit all buſie diſcourſe touching his office, whether he were <hi>Steward of the houſe,</hi> as ſome Writers reade: or as <hi>Iunius</hi> renders it, <hi>praefectus praetorio,</hi> one that had the ordering of the men of warre and marſhall affaires: or whether he were <hi>Scriba honorarius,</hi> principall Secretary, as the ſtorie hath it, the 2 of Kings at the 18. or,<note place="margin">2 Kings 18.</note> whether he were <hi>keeper of the Rolles,</hi> or, <hi>Maſter of Requeſts,</hi> as elſe-where our Prophet ſeemes to imply,<note place="margin">Iſay 36.3.</note> 
               <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 36.3. wee may boldly reſt on this, that he was a prime man in that ſtate, and indeed raiſed to that height of honor, or at leaſt continued at that height of honor (vntill he deſerued the contrary) as that higher hee could not goe,<note place="margin">Junius.</note> euen ſo high <hi>quantum potuit eſſe viri</hi> ſaith one, as poſſibly a ſubiect could be capable of. He was <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundus à Rege,</hi> the Kings right hand, and as it ſhould ſeeme by the deſcription of <hi>Eliachims</hi> power and authoritie, who ſucceeded <hi>Shebna</hi> both in place and greatneſſe,<note place="margin">Iſay 22.22.</note> he had the very key of <hi>Dauid,</hi> and bare ſuch ſway, as that all men ſought vnto him, all, euen from him that ſate vpon the throne, to him that grinded at the mill, relied on him: The King for aduice, the people for dependance, and
<pb facs="tcp:17988:5"/>there was no one thing done, either in Church or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, either at home or abroad, that <hi>Shebna</hi> was not priuy too: nay, ſuch accompt made <hi>Ezechiah</hi> of this one <hi>Shebna,</hi> and ſuch truſt and confidence he repoſed in him, as that when <hi>Zenacherib</hi> threatned the ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction both of <hi>Ezechiah</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> why, <hi>Shebna</hi> was a man, and a chiefe man ſent from <hi>Ezechiah</hi> to appeaſe <hi>Zenacherib</hi> and diuert him from his bloudy deſigne. In a word: when I conſider either the place that <hi>Shebna</hi> bare in the common wealth, or the good opinion ſhall I ſay? nay, the ſtrong confidence, truſt and repoſe, which <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiah</hi> had in him; mee thinks I heare <hi>Ezechiah</hi> ſpeake vnto <hi>Shebna</hi> as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> vnto <hi>Ioſeph,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 41.40.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt be ouer mine houſe and of thy word ſhall all my people be armed, onely in the Kings throne will I be aboue thee. Gen.</hi> 41.40. Mee thinkes hee no leſſe reſpected him,<note place="margin">Eſter 6.8.</note> then <hi>Aſſuerus</hi> did <hi>Mordecay</hi> in the ſixt of Eſter at the 8 verſe: or <hi>Balthaſar</hi> him that could in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret the dreame <hi>Dan:</hi> 5.7. For,<note place="margin">Dan: 5.7.</note> 
               <hi>Ecce</hi> (as Iunius hath it) <hi>Iehouah contegit to in tegumento, &amp; amiciendo amicit te bellè.</hi> and what poſſibly can you name ſhould be <hi>done to the man whom the King would honor,</hi> that was not done to <hi>Shebna.</hi> Hee had honor, wealth, power, command, and which is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall, nay aboue all the reſt, hee had the fauor and good opinion of his Soueraigne, and what could the large and vaſte heart of any reaſonable ſubiect deſire more?</p>
            <p>But <hi>O ignominia domus Domini!</hi> you would wonder to ſee how ſoone this baſe fellow and earthly meteor, but now drawne aloft by the beames of the Princes fauour, vaniſht; and how quickly his <hi>good ſeruice</hi> (as <hi>Lewis</hi> the XI. King of France was wont to ſay) <hi>vtterly vndid him</hi> (ſo that,<note place="margin">Phil. de Com. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quem vidit veniens dies ſuperbum, Hunc vidit fugiens dies ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For, <hi>Shebna</hi> looking vpon theſe bleſſings of God and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uors of his Prince, as Swine vpon maſte, neuer lifting vp his heart or entertayning ſo much as a thankfull thought from whence they fell, ſo exaſperated God the author and doner of them, that he ſeemeth here, as ſometime hee did vpon a
<pb facs="tcp:17988:6"/>ſerious view and conſideration of the old world, euen to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent that euer he made <hi>Shebna</hi> a man, or at leaſt ſo great a man; and therefore he ſends our Prophet here, and giues him in charge without any the leaſt delay or preadmoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whatſoeuer, to lay the axe vnto the roote of the tree and ſmite home.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Goe get thee vnto this Treaſurer, euen vnto Shebna which is ouer the houſe, and ſay.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>But of Gods round and peremptorie dealing with <hi>Sheb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> I ſhall haue occaſion to ſpeake, when I come to the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of his offence: I am yet come no further, then the qualitie of his perſon, what he was, a man, who kept all other in awe, a man, of royall entertainment: a man, of prime note and eminencie, a pillar of the ſtate, a patrone of the people, a fauorite of the King.</p>
            <p>The vſe whereof may be that in the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Man being in honor hath no vnderſtanding,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal: 49.13.</note> 
               <hi>hee is like to beaſts that periſh.</hi> Pſal. 49.13. eſpecially that man that riſeth from a low and meane eſtate, none more inſolent, none more ingratefull, none greater deſpiſers of others, magnifiers of themſelues.</p>
            <p>And it may ſerue to admoniſh ſuch as riſe from meane parentage, birth and eſtate, to looke vnto the rocke from whence they were hewen, and in all humilitie and hearty acknowledgment of Gods goodnes towards them, to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry themſelues fairely and reſpectiuely to others. Whereas ſuch is the impotencie and weakneſſe of many, that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue it when you will, you ſhall ſeldome ſee men baſe by birth, baſe by deſcent, baſe by education, but if once they get into the ſtirrup and climbe to any place of honour, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, meanes, command, why, preſently they begin to play the <hi>Shebna,</hi> and as the Poet ſaith of drunken men, and what greater drunkenneſſe then this of the minde? <hi>Tum ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niunt riſus, tum pauper cornua ſumit.</hi> And this ſhall ſuffice to haue been ſpoken of the qualitie of his perſon, <hi>what he was.</hi> I come now by your good fauour, to the nature of his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17988:6"/>
               <hi>what he did. Go get thee vnto this Treaſurer euen vnto Shebna which is ouer the houſe, &amp; ſay.</hi>
               <note place="margin">What was his offence.</note> As touching the offence of <hi>Shebna,</hi> it will aske ſome time to finde it out, but being found out it will appeare to be a maruellous great one, no leſſe then <hi>Treaſon,</hi> a <hi>tranſcendent Treaſon,</hi> and euery way de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing the ſeuereſt puniſhment.</p>
            <p>There are that haue taken great paines to finde out the ſinne of <hi>Shebna,</hi> and they ſticke not to charge him with <hi>arrogancie, vaine-glory, ſecuritie, contempt of God and his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, exaction, extortion, oppreſſion, ſcandall, and bad example,</hi> with which, as one ſaith, hee did more hurt, then with all the reſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cyrill</hi> deſcribeth him to be, <hi>elato animo, ſupercilioſum ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum ac ſaenum in eos à quibus erat offenſus, rapinis exultan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, ſordido quoeſtui mancipatum, oſtentabundum, &amp; honores ab alijs ſemper venantem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether <hi>Shebna</hi> were guilty of any one or all theſe, I will not ſay, but ſure I am when wee ſhall lay all theſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they will not make vp the full meaſure of <hi>Shebna his impiety,</hi> they will not amount to the offence of <hi>Shebna,</hi> ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what elſe there was in all likely hood, which did exaſperate God ſo greatly againſt him.</p>
            <p>If you pleaſe to goe no further then our Prophets com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion here, to the very words of my text, it will appeare without any the leaſt ſtrayning, euen from the bare letter thereof, that there was another notorious ſinne in <hi>Shebna,</hi> beſides all thoſe which now were named, and that is his ſin of <hi>Hypocriſie,</hi> in that God ſaith here, <hi>Go get thee vnto this, this Treaſurer.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> where the particle <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is put for contempt ſaith <hi>Caluin.</hi> As if it had been ſaid. <hi>Goe get thee to this Cercops</hi> (as they called <hi>Iulian</hi>) to this ſubtle and wilie fox, to this <hi>Amphiſbaena,</hi> this two headed and double-hearted ſerpent <hi>Shebna.</hi> So that did we goe no farther then his hypocriſie, why here you ſee is fewell enough for Gods fierce and vnquenchable wrath to worke vpon. For <hi>we are but of yeſterday, and are ignorant. Inquire therefore I pray you of the former age, and call to minde ancient experiments,</hi> and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17988:7"/>they will tell you the guerdon and reward of an <hi>Hypocrite</hi> at the hands of Gods, <hi>did you euer ſee a ruſh grow without mire? or can the graſſe grow without water, though it were in greene, and not cut downe, yet it ſhall wither before any other hearbe: So are the paths of all that forget God, and the hypocrites hope ſhall periſh. His confidence alſo ſhall be cut off and his truſt ſhall be as the houſe of a ſpider.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 8. ver: 11.12.13.14.15.</note> 
               <hi>Hee ſhall leane vpon his houſe but it ſhall not ſtand: he ſhall hold him fast by it, yet ſhall it not indure.</hi> Loe here the reward of an hypocrite, and <hi>Shebna</hi> was an hypocrite: but yet this was not <hi>the</hi> ſinne of <hi>Shebna.</hi> Adde vnto his hypocriſie,<note place="margin">Eſay 22.16.</note> what we finde in the 16 verſe, to wit, his notorious ambition. In that <hi>Shebna</hi> being <hi>homo nouus, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis,</hi> a meere ſtranger, and which is more an Aegyptian ſtranger, with whom neither <hi>Ezechiah</hi> himſelfe, nor any of his ſubiects ought to haue had the leaſt commerce, or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercourſe, and who by the law was excluded from all title of honour, or place of gouernment in that common wealth; yet notwithſtanding this ſtranger, this Aegyptian, this <hi>Sheb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> preſumed to ranke himſelfe with the bloud royall, the nobles and princes of Iudah, and omitted no one point of pompe and magnificence, whereby he might ſupport him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the eyes of the world during his naturall life, and that once ended aeternize his name among them for euer. And therfore our Prophet begins with him as <hi>Achilles</hi> with that brauing and cracking <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Homer: Iliad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> after a round and rough manner, by way of high indignation and great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>? <hi>quis vnde hominum es? What hast thou to doe heere? And whom haſt thou heere?</hi> that heere of all other coaſts and countries, where thou haſt leaſt inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and canſt not intitle thy ſelfe to any the leaſt clod of earth, that heere I ſay, thou ſhouldeſt prepare and erect ſo rich and ſo ſumptuous a tombe in ſo high and eminent a place aboue others.</p>
            <p>Adde vnto his <hi>Ambition,</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 18.</note> his <hi>Ingratitude</hi> in the 18 verſe, where our Prophet calls <hi>ignominia domus Domini,</hi> the ſhame and ſcandall and diſhonour of his Lord and Maſter: now, <hi>ingratum dixeris, omnia dixeris,</hi> there is no fault, no
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17988:7"/>vice whatſoeuer, but you ſhall finde it more or leſſe in an vngratefull perſon, and <hi>Shebna</hi> was ingratefull, but yet this was not now <hi>the</hi> ſinne of <hi>Shebna.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Adde therefore I pray you one ſinne more, and then we ſhall come neere the ſinne of <hi>Shebna:</hi> and that is, the <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reconcileable hatred,</hi> deſpite, enuy, detraction, wherewith he daily and hourely hunted, and perſecuted honeſt and harmeleſſe <hi>Eliachim,</hi> ſtill whiſpering and buſſing in the eares of the King, ſome infamous ſlander or vnchriſtian ſurmiſe, whereby he might bring innocent <hi>Eliachim</hi> in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace both with Prince and people, as we may gather out of the 20. verſe. O this is a ſinne of all ſinnes!<note place="margin">verſ: 20.</note> when a cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Belial</hi> and ſlandering <hi>Shebna</hi> ſhall hate goodneſſe in any for no other reaſon but becauſe he will hate, when hee ſhall carry a throat as wide as an open ſepulchre, and tip his tongue with the poyſon of Aſpes, when hee ſhall bend his bow and make ready his arrowes, of detractrion, malice, ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, reports, ſuggeſtions, lies, and all to deuoure poyſon, and ſhoot ſecretly <hi>(Lord into their ſecret let not my ſoule come)</hi> at the ſimple and vpright of life, and that when his furie is ouer, his paſſion ſetled and he come vnto himſelfe, neither he nor the deuill that ſet him a worke is able to ſay, what hath the righteous done? O this is one and a principall one, of thoſe <hi>peccata clamantia,</hi> which as they oft-times pierce the tender hearts of Gods deare children, (the more their weakneſſe and want of true Chriſtian fortitude) ſo do they with all importunitie knocke at the gates of heauen, and crie aloud for Gods heauy and vnſupportable venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance on the doers of them. And thus haue yee at length a liſt of <hi>Shebnaes</hi> foule ſinnes and offences. <hi>Shebna</hi> was an <hi>hypocrite, Shebna</hi> was <hi>ambitious, Shebna</hi> was <hi>ingratefull, Shebna</hi> was <hi>enuious</hi> and giuen ouer to thoſe crying ſinnes of detraction, ſupplanting, ſlandering, lying, and what not, but yet we haue not named <hi>the</hi> ſinne of <hi>Shebna,</hi> the particular capitall crime, the predominant ſinne of <hi>Shebna</hi> which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waked Gods iuſtice and prouoked him thus in all ſeueritie to proceed againſt him. For all theſe which but now I na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17988:8"/>
               <hi>hypocrifie, ambition, ingratitude, enuy,</hi> why they were rather <hi>peccata hominum, peccata Iudaeorum,</hi> then any appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated ſinnes of <hi>Shebna,</hi> they were ſinnes incident to the corrupt nature of man: familiar to the people of the Iewes and cannot by way of denomination be termed <hi>the ſinnes</hi> of <hi>Shebna. Inſita est mortalibus naturâ,</hi> ſaith he, men by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are wholy giuen to taxe and maligne vertue and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in others <hi>&amp; pari dolore aliena commoda, ac proprias iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rias metiri</hi> and to take other mens benefits and bleſſings as much to heart as their owne proper iniuries. But eſpecially the Iewes, no people, no nation ſo giuen ouer to <hi>hypocriſie, ambition, ingratitude</hi> and <hi>enuy</hi> as the Iewes.</p>
            <p>Beſides, it is worth the noting, that God proceedeth after another faſhion with the Princes of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and the reſt of the inferiour ſort of people, and puniſheth their offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in another kinde, as he that will peruſe the former part of this Chapter may eaſily perceiue, and I as eaſily ſhew you, could I now ſtay. But when he cals to minde the ſinne of <hi>Shebna,</hi> he bids our Prophet addreſſe himſelfe to <hi>Shebna</hi> in particular, as vnto a ſupereminent notorious offender aboue all the reſt: <hi>Goe get thee vnto this Treaſurer, euen vnto Shebna, which is ouer the houſe, and ſay.</hi> It was not then his hypocriſie, it was not his ambition, nor yet his ingratitude, no nor yet his enuie: it was a ſinne of a deeper die, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied I grant you with all theſe, but yet not any one of all theſe.</p>
            <p>And that was his ſinne of <hi>Treaſon. Shebna</hi> was a Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, <hi>patriae proditor,</hi> which (as one ſaith) comes <hi>à prodendis conſilijs hoſtibus:</hi> ſo that <hi>Shebna</hi> (as I verily thinke) reuealed both <hi>arcana dominationis &amp; domus,</hi> ſecrets of State, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of Court, and moſt treacherouſly combined to betray <hi>Ezechiah</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> into the hands of a profeſſed ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie and atheall miſcreant <hi>Zenacherib,</hi> as hoping forſooth that when once <hi>Zenacherib</hi> ſhould be veſted in the Throne of <hi>Iudah,</hi> he would thinke on <hi>Shebna,</hi> and make him King ouer his owne Countrey at the leaſt. And this I take to be the ſinne of <hi>Shebna.</hi> As for thoſe other ſinnes, I make no
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17988:8"/>doubt but <hi>Shebna</hi> had of a long time nouriſhed them, and God might ſay vnto him as it is in the Pſalmiſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 49.21.</note> 
               <hi>Haec feciſti &amp; tacui:</hi> Theſe things haſt thou done, <hi>Shebna,</hi> and I held my peace. But when once he committed the ſinne of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, then was it high time for God, who as the ſonne of <hi>Siracke</hi> ſaith, <hi>patient est etiam &amp; redditor,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Wiſdome.</note> to come downe and viſit <hi>Shebna</hi> with a rod of iron.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Goe get thee vnto this Treaſurer, euen vnto Shebna, that is ouer the houſe; and ſay.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Shebna</hi> then was a Traitor, his offence Treaſon, nay, I added more, a <hi>tranſcendent Treaſon:</hi> For looke vpon the moſt hainous Treaſons and bloudie aſſaſſinats in the bookes of the Chronicles of the Kings of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and other faithfull ſtories in the word of God, you ſhall finde ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what that will leſſen them, and giue occaſion of extenuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. In all of them you ſhall obſerue that fleſh and bloud will haue ſome Sanctuarie to flie vnto; and an indulgent obſeruer will eaſily inuent arguments to mitigate, if not quite to purge the fouleneſſe of each offence. But <hi>Shebna</hi> his treaſon was ſo dangerous and inexcuſable, that it will admit of no extenuation.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond of <hi>Eſter</hi> you ſhall reade of a dangerous treaſon attempted by <hi>Bigthan</hi> and <hi>Tereſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſter 2.</note> vpon the body of an annointed King, the King <hi>Aſſuerus;</hi> where, if we looke vpon the authors of the treaſon, it was very dangerous and inexcuſable: for what could not theſe miſchieuous villaines doe, that were Squires of the body, and had the life and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the King in their owne cuſtodie? But yet if wee caſt our eie vpon the obiect of their treaſon, why ſurely it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended no farther, neither had they any other obiect, then the bare life only of <hi>Aſſuerus</hi> at the moſt.</p>
            <p>In the third of that booke you ſhall finde recorded a bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous maſſacre intended by <hi>Haman</hi> againſt the perſon, not of one or two, but euen of <hi>Mordecay</hi> and the people of <hi>Mordecay.</hi> Heere now if you looke narrowly vpon the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17988:9"/>of the obiect, <hi>Mordecay</hi> and all the Iewes, verily the crueltie of mercileſſe <hi>Haman</hi> can no way be extenuated: but yet if you will ſearch a little farther, and enquire after the end he propoſed vnto himſelfe, we cannot ſay that the life of his liege Lord, or that the welfare of the proper in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of that Countrey, or that the preſeruation of the ſtate wherein he liued, and whereof hee was a principall member, was any way put in hazard: onely <hi>Mordecay</hi> and certaine Iewes diſperſed vp and downe thorowout the Kings prouinces were aimed at.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond of <hi>Samuel</hi> at the 15 we haue ſtoried a foule and vnnaturall treacherie of <hi>Abſolon</hi> againſt his father <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 15.</note> where if we marke well the end he propoſed vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, to wit, the vſurpation of the Kingdome, or the meanes he vſed for the atchieuing of this his end, namely by ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling away the hearts of the people, <hi>ſollicitando, pollicitando,</hi> (as <hi>Simo</hi> chargeth <hi>Crito</hi> in the Comedie) feeding their fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies with affable geſtures and faire promiſes, by getting armes and militarie forces into his hands, by quarrelling the execution of iuſtice and courſe of gouernment, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luding his father with a pretence of performing his vow, and the more free ſeruing of God, and a world of ſuch like traiterous lies and deuices, nothing can be ſaid for it. But yet if you will weigh the iſſue and euent which in probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie muſt needs haue followed, you will not thinke it ſo hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous: for the worſt that can be ſaid or feared, was but the change of a Prince, of the father for the ſonne, of an old for a new: the Law ſhould haue remained the ſame, the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion the ſame, the gouernment the ſame, and there would haue enſued little or no inuerſion, much leſſe euerſion of the ſtate. So that in all theſe, though dangerous and inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable treaſons and murders in themſelues, yet ſomewhat there is that a man partially affected may picke out to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge, if not for defence, yet for excuſe and extenuation of them. But <hi>Shebna</hi> his treaſon heere is like a ſtrong poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon compoſed of whatſoeuer was moſt bad in the worſt of theſe. And it was dangerous and inexcuſable, not onely in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17988:9"/>regard of the author, as that of the Eunuches; nor yet of the obiect, as that of <hi>Hamans;</hi> nor yet of the end and meanes which he vſed, as that of <hi>Abſolon:</hi> but in all theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, both of author, obiect, end, euent, euery way.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, it was dangerous and inexcuſable in regard of the author who committed it, <hi>Shebna.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And heere I muſt intreat you to conceiue of <hi>Shebna</hi> not as now we finde him, diſmantled and detected by our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, but as then he was when he firſt hatched and concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued this treaſon. For conſpiracies and treaſons are like ſparkes of fire, which in the darke and deepe hearts of Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors glitter, and are lightſome, probable, and very likely to take effect: but when as they Sunne ſhines on them, and that they are diſcouered, they fall to aſhes. Euery childe can paſſe a iudgement vpon the euent and ſucceſſe of a deſigne. But we muſt not thinke Traitors ſo fooliſh as the euent, or rather God (whoſe glorie it is to raine <hi>ſnares, fire and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 11.6.</note> 
               <hi>and ſtormie tempeſt</hi> vpon the miſchieuous machinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of treacherous wretches) in the euent and concluſion makes them. He replied with great indignation, when led to the Tower a friend told him, <hi>Ah my Lord, I am ſorry you had no more wit:</hi> Tuſh (quoth he) thou knoweſt not what thou ſaieſt; <hi>When ſaweſt thou a foole come hither?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And you ſhall neuer reade of any treaſon, eſpecially ſuch a compleat treaſon as this of <hi>Shebnaes,</hi> but it was attempted by ſuch as were great promiſers vnto themſelues, confident of their wit, ſecure of the ſucceſſe, and ſuch as made no more difficultie to effect then to affect a treaſon: and ſuch a one was <hi>Shebna.</hi> Wherefore let vs take <hi>Shebna</hi> as hee was when he firſt plotted and contriued this treaſon, and then tell me if he carried not the matter dangerouſly, if hee did not as much a any man of his ſpirit and working diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on could haue done for the vtter ouerthrow of <hi>Ezechiah</hi> and the whole Land of <hi>Iudah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For firſt, he tooke the ſame courſe that all deepe Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors euer haue and will take, whoſe manner is to pretend one thing, when in heart they intend another; and like
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17988:10"/>
               <hi>Lapwings,</hi> to flutter moſt and crie loudeſt, when they are fartheſt from their neſt; or with bote-men, to looke one way, and row another.</p>
            <p>Thus to omit all forraine inſtances, whereof there is no ſtorie ſo barren, but it hath ſtore and plentie, thus I ſay the Traitor <hi>Digbie</hi> pretends a match of hunting, while his heart lay among the crowes of iron, the piles of billets, and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels of pouder in the nethermoſt vault. Thus <hi>Parry,</hi> more <hi>to prepare acceſſe and credit, then for any care had of her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties perſon,</hi> the late Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of euer bleſſed me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, came to the Court, praied audience, diſcouered the coniuration, but yet (as himſelfe confeſſed) couered <hi>with all the skill he had,</hi> hee diſcloſed only ſo much as hee thought good and neceſſarie to ground in her Highneſſe a ſetled confidence towards him, whereby hee might effect his traiterous intent with better opportunitie, and his owne ſafetie.</p>
            <p>Right ſo, <hi>Shebna</hi> tenders his ſeruice to the King his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, ioines in commiſſion with <hi>Eliachim</hi> and <hi>Ioah,</hi> parlies with <hi>Rabſhakeh</hi> chiefe Coronell of <hi>Zenacheribs</hi> hoſt, laieth out an huge ſumme of money vpon a coſtly and glorious Tombe, and all to diuert the obſeruation of the ſtate, and beare them in hand he minded nothing more then to liue and die amongſt them, when notwithſtanding hee held in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence with the enemie, and vnder theſe pretences tooke the more libertie to play the profeſſed Traitor, and recommend his loue and ſeruice to <hi>Zenacherib.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, <hi>Shebna</hi> was not alone, he was not ſingular and ſelfe-conceited: it is probable a great part of the people (<hi>for the leaudeſt men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tacit.</note> ſaith <hi>Tacitus, miſdoubting the preſent, and fearing the change, prepare before hand friends</hi>) they alſo held it ſafeſt to doe as <hi>Shebna</hi> did, and cloſe with <hi>Zena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherib,</hi> as being perhaps animated thereunto partly by the ſubmiſſion of <hi>Ahaz,</hi> who had ſworne fealtie and homage to <hi>Tiglath Pileſer</hi> King of <hi>Aſhur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Reg. 16.7.</note> the ſecond of Kings, the ſixteenth chapter and ſeuenth verſe: and partly alſo by the diſhonourable carriage of <hi>Ezechiah</hi> himſelfe, who vpon the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17988:10"/>firſt aſſault, brake out into a moſt baſe and vnbeſeeming acknowledgement, <hi>I haue offended, depart from mee, and what thou laieſt vpon me I will beare it:</hi> the ſecond of <hi>Kings,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Reg. 18.14.</note> the eighteenth.</p>
            <p>And now I pray helpe me. Wherein tro you lay <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiahs</hi> ſtrength, or what was there in <hi>Ezechiah,</hi> or the fence and munition of <hi>Iudah,</hi> that could encourage any man of that experience and vnderſtanding that <hi>Shebna</hi> was, to ſtand out againſt <hi>Zenacherib?</hi> Lay it in the multitude of his people? <hi>Zenacherib</hi> had two for one. Lay it in their firme adherence and conſtancie? which is the chiefeſt thing a King can take comfort in in the time of w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re, where, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid, <hi>the ſword deuoureth the one as well as the other,</hi> the ſecond of <hi>Samuel,</hi> the eleuenth; and where,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 11.25.</note> as <hi>Hanni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal</hi> in <hi>Liuie</hi> tels vs, <hi>nuſquam minus euentus ſolent reſpondere,</hi> only if the people be firme and conſtant, and carrie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues like loyall and louing ſubiects, ther's ſome comfort. But alas who knoweth not <hi>populi mobilem animum, &amp; fi ſe ducem prabniſſet Zenacherib,</hi> as hee ſaith of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſpaſian,</hi> they would haue borne the ſame affection and demonſtration of loue and loyaltie to <hi>Zenacherib,</hi> which now they made ſhew of to <hi>Ezechiah:</hi> it being true of the common people in generall, that they doe nothing vpon iudgement or any true meaning, but vpon a receiued habituall kinde of ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morouſneſſe to ſway with the Prince whatſoeuer hee be; eſpecially of this people, who were as timorous as Harts, and as wauering as the winde: and therefore vpon a ſlighter occaſion, and leſſe danger, the Prophet ſaith, all were ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken with ſuch aſtoniſhment, that none could hold a ioint ſtill, but quiuered and trembled like ſo many aſpen leaues, <hi>Iſay.</hi> 7.2. As alſo in the originall ſtorie it ſelfe,<note place="margin">Iſay 7.2.</note> 1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 18. and in our Prophet at the 36. chapter you ſhall finde that <hi>Ezechiahs</hi> Embaſſadors craued this as an eſpeciall fauour of <hi>Rabſhekeh,</hi> that hee would not ſpeake vnto them in the Iewes tongue in the audience of the people that were on the wall, becauſe they were naturally mutable, ſaith <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin,</hi> and inconſtant, and ſuddenly drawne to reuolt. So
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17988:11"/>that had <hi>Zenacherib</hi> ſped and got the vpper hand, there was no doubt but the common people <hi>illa ipſa diceret hora Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtum.</hi> Adde heereunto the greatneſſe of <hi>Shebnaes</hi> place and power to doe miſchiefe, being (as was ſaid) <hi>praefectus praetorio,</hi> or principall Secretarie, and therefore priuie to all the ſecrets of State, thoſe <hi>arcana Imperij,</hi> and might giue <hi>Zenacherib</hi> perfect intelligence. Adde his ſtrength of wit to inuent miſchiefe, and ſecure himſelfe: his knowledge of the State, how weake and vnable to reſiſt: the opportunitie he now had (being the only man of truſt, <hi>Eliachim</hi> and <hi>Ioah</hi> excepted) to deale with the enemie.</p>
            <p>And laſtly this plauſibleneſſe with the people, being (as <hi>Iunitus</hi> cals him) <hi>fautor &amp; magiſter impiorum,</hi> and (as in all good confirmation we may gheſſe) <hi>pullus &amp; puppus,</hi> the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and darling of the multitude. So that though hee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into a deſperate peece of ſeruice, where his life and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and all lay at ſtake, yet hee did nothing but what hee ſaw and knew they would ſecond.</p>
            <p>And now tell me whether this were not a dangerous treaſon, if we goe no farther then the author, who you ſee had made all ſo ſure, that it was euen <hi>tempus faciendi Domino,</hi> high time for God to put his helping hand; otherwiſe the power of <hi>Zenacherib</hi> without, the inconſtancie of the leau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſort of people within, conſidered, <hi>Shebna</hi> went as neere as the wit of a man, actuated by the deuill himſelfe, the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of all miſchieuous ſubtiltie and deepe deuices, could goe, to compaſſe the ruine and deſtruction, not of one <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuerus,</hi> or a <hi>Mordecay,</hi> and thoſe of his <hi>Religion;</hi> but of his liege Lord and maſter <hi>Ezechiah,</hi> and the whole Land of <hi>Iudah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heere now the obiect and the latitude of the obiect much aggrauates <hi>Shebna</hi> his treaſon.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Shebna</hi> aimed not at the ruine of a priuate man, which had beene bad and inexcuſable, ſith (as one ſaith) <hi>domeſtica &amp; familiaris Deo eſt hominis natura:</hi> and <hi>quicunque effuderit humanum ſanguinem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 9.6.</note> 
               <hi>per hominem fundetur ſanguis illius: Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſis</hi> 9.6.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:17988:11"/>
            <p>Neither leueld <hi>Shebna</hi> at <hi>Eliachim</hi> alone, at ſome chiefe Magiſtrate or Sentinell of the ſtate, which had been worſe, ſith publike Miniſters ſtand for thouſands and hundreds: they are the <hi>charets and horſemen</hi> of a common-wealth,<note place="margin">2 Regu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 2.12.</note> they are Gods <hi>Lieutenants</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icegerents on earth,</hi> and therfore the leaſt contempt, the leaſt ſiniſter thought tending to their hurt, God takes as done vnto himſelfe.</p>
            <p>But as thoſe two and thirty Captaines in the 1 of Kings and the two and twentieth,<note place="margin">1 Regu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 22.31.</note> did <hi>Shoot neither at ſmall nor great, ſaue at the King himſelfe:</hi> ſo <hi>Shebnah</hi> his chiefe aime was at the King, and this King was <hi>Ezechiah,</hi> I ſay <hi>Ezechiah,</hi> ſo that here <hi>Shebna</hi> his treaſon appeares in it's full bigneſſe, ſith there was more in <hi>Ezechiah</hi> then can be verified of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, I had almoſt ſaid of any King beſides, and therefore the more eminent and worthy the Prince, the more vile and inexcuſable the traytor, the more goodly the obiect, the fouler the treaſon.</p>
            <p>For firſt, had <hi>Ezechiah</hi> been a King onely by conqueſt, without iuſt title to the crowne: this fact of <hi>Shebna</hi> had been the leſſe, ſith Kings by conqueſt are no better than great theeues.<note place="margin">Auguſtine.</note> Elegant and excellent was the Pirats anſwer to the great <hi>Macedonian Alexander</hi> ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> in his 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> booke <hi>de ciuitate Dei</hi> and 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> chapter. The King asking him, <hi>how he durſt molest the ſea ſo?</hi> hee replied with a free ſpirit ſaith the Father, <hi>how dareſt thou molest the whole world?</hi> but becauſe I doe it with one onely Galley-foiſt, I am called a theife, thou doing it with a great Nauie art called an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour. And <hi>Lucan</hi> makes no ſcruple to terme <hi>Alexander</hi> a happy theife of the earth,</p>
            <q>
               <l>— <hi>Terrarum fatale malum.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Earths fatall miſchiefe and a cloud of thunder</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Renting the world: a ſtarre that ſtrucke in ſunder</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Nations.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>Conquerors then, whoſe right is their power, are theeues, and there is ſuch an <hi>antipathie</hi> between the Conqueror and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17988:12"/>the conquered, that it is impoſſible for ſubiects of any good bloud truly and in heart to loue a Conquerour; whervpon it is, that the Politiques giue a precept, and their ſchollers put it in practiſe, <hi>A Conqueror,</hi> ſay they, <hi>must ſubuert and deſtroy all ſuch as ſuffer great loſſe in that Conquest, and altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther roote out the bloud and the race of ſuch as before gouerned there.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This doctrine <hi>Thraſibulus</hi> taught, when he led a Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger into a field of corne and bruiſed the talleſt eares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween his hands, and this from him <hi>Periander</hi> practiſed, when hee tooke out of the way the chiefe and nobleſt men of <hi>Corinth.</hi> This <hi>Tarquin</hi> the proud commended to <hi>Sex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> his ſonne, when he cut off <hi>ſumma papauerum capita,</hi> and this <hi>Sextus</hi> accordingly put in vre, when hee cauſed to be maſſacred in their houſes, all the greateſt and nobleſt of the towne of <hi>Gabium.</hi> But <hi>Ezechiah</hi> was no ſuch bloudy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror. <hi>Hee was an abſolute Monarch and free borne King.</hi> Secondly, had <hi>Ezechiah</hi> been offenſiue or burdenſome to his ſubiects, or diſſolute in his gouernment, <hi>Shebna</hi> might haue had ſome pretence.<note place="margin">Bellar: de Rom: Pon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: lib. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> For though I am not of their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion who teach that Kings receiue their Crownes from men, and hold them at their diſpoſe, yet I reſt aſſured that the vertue, worth and affable vſage of a Prince are they that gaine and keepe the affections of the people; whereas on the other ſide, the enormious defects and harſh vſage of a King alienates their mindes from him, as from one that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſeth his Soueraigntie, and cauſeth them to flie to others, whom they hold more fit to command, and vnto whom they are more willing to yeeld obedience. A Prince, as he is aboue others in place, ſo he ſhould ſhine aboue others in vertue; pettie blemiſhes in a Prince breed a loathing in the ſubiect: their leaſt defects are ſoone ſpied and as ſoone cenſured. <hi>Qui magno imperio praediti, in excelſo aetatem agunt, eorum facta cuncti mortales nouere. Ita in maxima fortuna mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nima licentia est</hi> (ſaith <hi>Caeſar</hi> in <hi>Saluſt.</hi>) <hi>ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſtudere, neque o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſe ſed minimè <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>aſci debet. Quae apud alios Iracundia dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ea imperij ſuperbia at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> crudelitas appellatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:17988:12"/>
            <p>The ill-willers of <hi>Pompey</hi> the great, obſeruing that now and then he ſcratched his head with one finger, thought the worſe of him for that. The <hi>Athenians</hi> found fault with <hi>Simon</hi> becauſe he loued to drinke a cup of good wine. And the <hi>Romans</hi> finding no other thing in that famous Leader <hi>Scipio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plutarch: pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cep: pol.</note> tooke occaſion to blame him (ſaith <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his precepts of policie) onely for <hi>ſleeping.</hi> For like as a little freckle, a little mole or pendant wart in the face of a man or woman is more offenſiue then blacke and blew marks, then ſcarrs and maimes in all the reſt of the body; euen ſo, ſmall and light faults otherwiſe of themſelues, ſhew great in the liues of Princes, ſaith that author. Now if men be ſo apt to take offence at ſuch pettie ſcapes as theſe, what will they not doe, when they deſcry thoſe prints of tyrannie, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, breach of promiſes and othes, frauds and deceit, and all kinde of iniuſtice; he will tell you <hi>Qui ſceptra duro ſaeuus imperio regit, timet timentes.</hi> And <hi>Tully, No force or power of Empire be it neuer ſo great, can long ſtand, if it be preſt with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall feare and hatred of the ſubiects.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Comminaeus.</note> Memorable is that which <hi>Comminaeus</hi> ſets downe at large in his 7 booke &amp; 11. chapter, of <hi>Alphonſo</hi> a rich and potent King, who for that he forced his ſubiects to feed and fat his hoggs, for that hee bought vp all the oyle, and graine in the country before it was ripe, ſold <hi>Biſhopricks,</hi> gaue away <hi>Abbeyes</hi> to Falconers, and committed a many the like inſolencies, grew in the end deſpicable in the ſight of his people, and was forſaken of all.</p>
            <p>The like befell <hi>Lodouic Sforza</hi> Duke of <hi>Millan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Guice:</hi> Inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie of France, <hi>vita Lewis</hi> the 12.</note> who by his great exactions and impoſitions (ſaith <hi>Guicciardin</hi>) ſo exaſperated his ſubiects, that when <hi>Lewis</hi> the 12. came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, they forthwith tooke armes, killed his Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, forced him to flie, called in the French and yeelded the towne and themſelues to their obedience.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, <hi>Mathew</hi> of <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtminſter</hi> tells vs of King <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mathew Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter.</note> how that <hi>exoſum ſe praebuit,</hi> he made himſelfe hatefull vnto his people, as well for the murther of his nephew <hi>Arthur,</hi> as for his adulteries, his tyrannie, his exactions, and the like, in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17988:13"/>reſpect whereof <hi>Vix alicuius meruit lamentatione deplorari,</hi> he deſerued not to be lamented ſcarcely of any.</p>
            <p>How well and warrantably the ſubiects of theſe Kings demeaned themſelues, I leaue to your iudgement, I like it not. By theſe few examples you may ſee how apt the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are to grow in diſlike with their King, when hee once ceaſeth to be truly royall and by hard vſage alienateth their mindes and affections from him. But here was no ſuch matter, <hi>Shebna</hi> could not implead his Prince of any ſuch outrage. <hi>Ezechiah</hi> was a good and godly King, vnto whom the Scripture ſtill giues thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> teſtimonie, that <hi>he did vprightly in the ſight of the Lord, according to all that Dauid his father had done, he truſted in the Lord God of Iſrael. So that after him was none like vnto him among all the Kings of Iuda, neither were there any ſuch before him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Reg: 18.5.</note> 2 Kings 18.5.</p>
            <p>But this is not all, <hi>maius opus moueo &amp; maior mihi naſcitur ordo rerum,</hi> there was more in <hi>Ezechiah</hi> then all this. <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiah</hi> was a King, and a King of the line of Dauid. A King and a King of the tribe of Iudah, vnto both which God had bound himſelfe by ſo many promiſes and couenants as that he might as well faile to be what hee is, as not to be a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full protector of Iudah, and of the ſtocke of Dauid, ſaying, <hi>I haue ſworne once by my holineſſe that I will not faile Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal: 89.63.</note> 
               <hi>His ſeede ſhall endure for euer, and his throne ſhall be as the ſunne before me.</hi> Pſal. 89.36.</p>
            <q>
               <l>His ego nec metas rerum, nec tempora pono</l>
               <l>Imperium ſine fine dedi.</l>
            </q>
            <p>So that here as in a mirrour you may ſee <hi>Shebna</hi> his more then Luciferian pride, his Gygantomachia, in that being a poore finite wretch, a <hi>Typhon,</hi> a vaſſall, a bramble, hee durſt attempt that, which hee could not but know called in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, all thoſe holy and faithfull promiſes of that neuer-fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling keeper of Iudah and of the line of <hi>Dauid.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:17988:13"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">End. </seg>
               </label> And, <hi>cui bono?</hi> that I may let goe thoſe two former cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances the <hi>Author</hi> and the <hi>Obiect,</hi> and come to his end which he propoſed to himſelfe, and the meanes whereby he muſt obtaine this his end, to wit, that <hi>Shebna</hi> might bee a <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here may you obſerue a ſtrange point of nature in this Traitor, in that hee ſo impotently affected his owne priuat aduancement, as that hee cared not what became of <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiah</hi> or of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> or of the whole land of <hi>Iudah,</hi> ſo hee might bee a King. Nay, God himſelfe muſt goe from his word, fall from his promiſe, forſake his <hi>annoynted</hi> abandon his owne <hi>peculium</hi> and proper people, and all that <hi>Shebna may be a King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Deare Chriſt! what is this heart of man, how boundleſſe the deſires thereof? was it not enough for <hi>Shebna</hi> to bee glutted with the fauours of his Prince? was it enough for him (to ſpeake in the phraſe of the Poet) to detaine fortune captiue with all her treaſures, and carry in triumph the feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities of this world, <hi>glory, honor, riches,</hi> but <hi>Shebna</hi> muſt needs be a King. I, thats it, <hi>Shebna</hi> muſt be a King. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe his ambitious heart would pant and bray, and all this preſent greatneſſe and honor wherewith he wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> now inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, would but increaſe his griefe, ſinke him in Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholie, and driue him into a conſumption or worſe diſeaſe, ſo long as he was depriued of that which muſt crowne and actuate all the reſt, and giue vnto his aſpiring minde her full complacencie and contentment, and thats a kingdom. <hi>Shebna</hi> muſt be a <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ah poore <hi>Shebna: quid hoc putemus eſſe? qui modo ſcurra aut ſi quid hae re tricius videbatur.</hi> Muſt he now needs be a <hi>King?</hi> was it euer heard that a traitor was rewarded? did euer wiſe man thinke him worthy of any reward, but ſuch as is truly due vnto him, the gallowes? yet <hi>Shebna</hi> muſt be a King.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander</hi> the great (ſaith <hi>Iuſtin</hi>) at his Fathers obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17988:14"/>commanded publique <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> done vpon thoſe whom he had himſelfe ſecretly imployed to kill him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tiberius</hi> (ſaith <hi>Tacitus</hi> in the firſt of his <hi>Annales</hi>) diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowed his commiſſion giuen to a ſouldier to kill <hi>Agrippa,</hi> telling him that he ſhould anſwer the matter before the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate. And howſoeuer men or rather monſters of men many times are contented to take the benefit of a ſeruice done by euill meanes: yet euer after they hold the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſuſpected, and hate the malitious nature and diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of him that doth it. Yet <hi>Shebna must be a King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Inuentor: of France, <hi>vita Henry</hi> the 3.</note>
               <hi>Iames Clement</hi> a Iacobine voweth to kill <hi>Henry</hi> the third of France, hee imparts his damnable proiect to Doctor <hi>Bourgoing Prior</hi> of his <hi>Couent,</hi> to Father <hi>Comelet</hi> and other Ieſuits, and to all the chiefe of the ſixteene, and to the forty of <hi>Paris.</hi> All incourage him to his happy deſigne, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe him <hi>Abbeyes</hi> and <hi>Biſhoprickes,</hi> and if he chance to bee made a Martyr, no leſſe then a place in heauen aboue the Apoſtles. This traitor thus incouraged, goes on, kills the King, and <hi>Paulus, Quintus</hi> ſpends a great deale of wit and inuention in commendation of the murther, it was <hi>rarum</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>inauditum, memorabile facinus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is abroad in the world that ſhames not to iuſtifie <hi>Rauillacs</hi> ſtabbing of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, late King of France, and ſaith it was not ſo much <hi>Rauillacs</hi> fault, as <hi>ſtoliditas Regis ob ſuſceptum haereticorum patrocinium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I know there are that mince that ſuperlatiue ſulphu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious treaſon. <hi>Alas it was but the attempt of ſome few, and thoſe vnfortunate Gentlemen, and that when they held the King, for no King or not their King, and laſtly, expectanda erat diutur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na perſecutio:</hi> and what will you neuer giue ouer, ſaith <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> that perſonated traytor, your clamors and exaggera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the <hi>Powder treaſon,</hi> the <hi>Powder treaſon:</hi> But tell mee if euer you read or heard of any that truly and in heart lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the traytor; yet <hi>Shebna</hi> muſt be a King.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:17988:14"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Meanes. </seg>
               </label> I but how or by what meanes ſay you muſt <hi>Shebna</hi> bee a King? why, <hi>ſollicitando, pollicitando,</hi> which was <hi>Abſolons</hi> courſe, and many traytors haue tane the like, and yet this is not all neither: a kingdome is not ſo eaſily gotten. But how then? Marry how haue greater ſpirits riſen from no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, or how grew the Romane Empire, to that magnitude and greatneſſe, or how haue high attempts been compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed beyond the expectation and reach of ſhallow and nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row wits ?</p>
            <p>Aske <hi>Liuie,</hi> and hee will tell you <hi>Agendo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib:</hi> 22.</note> 
               <hi>audendo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> res Romana creuit &amp;c.</hi> by doing and by daring the affaires of <hi>Rome</hi> increaſed, not by theſe dull and heauy counſels which timerous men terme warie. A wit too curious and caute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in caſting of doubts for the moſt part hurteth, and he that omitteth an opportunitie preſent, vpon ſuppoſed dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, ſhall neuer aduance his owne fortune.</p>
            <p>Goe to <hi>Cateſby</hi> heare what he ſaith: <hi>Wilt thou be a Traitor Tom? aude aliquid. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enture not thy ſelfe to ſmall purpoſe. If thou wilt be a traytor, there is a plot to greater aduantage, and ſuch a one as nere can be diſcouered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Good God! of what mould are theſe traytors made? or what wombe bare them? what difference and diſparitie there is between them and all good men? how infinitely come they ſhort of the cruelleſt heathens? Wee read that the elected Saints of God haue wiſhed themſelues <hi>Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed</hi> razed out of the booke of life, and vtterly excluded from the kingdome of heauen, for the publique good and preſeruation of Gods deare people: but <hi>Shebna</hi> here wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and plotteth the deſtruction and extirpation of Gods owne choſen peculiar people, and all that he may get a ſillie kingdome on earth.</p>
            <p>The moſt ambitious among the heathen, though they tooke an extraordinarie felicitie to imbrue their hands in bloud, to pill and depopulate whole townes and countries, yet they ſhooke not off all humanitie, they forgot not to be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17988:15"/>men, but had a feeling and were ſenſible of others calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and diſtreſſe. <hi>Alexander</hi> wept for <hi>Darius, Iulius Caeſar</hi> for <hi>Pompeius, Marcellus</hi> for <hi>Siracuſa,</hi> and <hi>Scipio</hi> for <hi>Numan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia.</hi> But ſo <hi>Shebna</hi> may be a King, <hi>Ezechiah, Ieruſalem,</hi> and that g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orious kingdome of <hi>Iudah</hi> muſt be expoſed to cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie it ſelfe, to ſacke and pillage, and all kinde of ſpoile and deuaſtation.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Euent. </seg>
               </label> For what other can wee imagine ſhould be the <hi>Euent</hi> of <hi>Shebna</hi> his treaſon, which was the fourth circumſtance, and comes now in it due place to aggrauate the foule inexcuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble treaſon of <hi>Shebna.</hi> For howſoeuer <hi>Shebna</hi> was not ſo wiſe as to foreſee, nor ſo honeſt as to feare what could not chooſe but follow, though <hi>Shebna</hi> propoſing to himſelfe his owne aduancement runne on blindfold and ſpied not the many many inconueniences and miſchiefes which would haue enſued, no nor cared not what might enſue, ſo he might be a <hi>King:</hi> yet ſucceeding ages ſaw and <hi>Iudah</hi> feared, and how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit a ſinne once committed be but one and the ſame, yet the hurt that ariſeth thereby much augments the venemous qualitie thereof, and thereafter as it doth dilate and ſpread and multiply to the preiudice and dammage of others, the more vile and dangerous and inexcuſable muſt it needs be.</p>
            <p>Let vs therefore ſee what hurt would haue inſued. And that will appeare by the predictions, threats, and forewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of that pſeudo prophet <hi>Rabſhekeh,</hi> who to make the people quake and tremble the more, ſets before them the miſeries and calamities into which they plunged them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, if they harkned to <hi>Ezechiah</hi> and ſtood out againſt <hi>Zenacherib.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hath my Maſter ſent me to thy Maſter, and to thee to ſpeake theſe words,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 36.12.</note> 
               <hi>and not to the men that ſit on the wall. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t comedant ſtercus ſuum &amp; bibant aquas pedum ſuorum.</hi> Iſai. 36.12. now</p>
            <q>
               <l>Dura quidem miſeris mors est mortalibus omnis:</l>
               <l>At perijſſe fame, res vna miſerrima longè est.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:17988:15"/>
            <p>But we ſhall not need to argue the euent from <hi>Rabſhekeh</hi> his threats, though I thinke he ſaid no more then what <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacherib</hi> would haue made good, and what <hi>Ezechiah</hi> and his people ſhould haue felt.</p>
            <p>You all know what are the proper immediate effects of warre and conqueſt; and therefore if you will needs haue me ſet downe what would haue enſued, I moſt earneſtly deſire you to remember (as <hi>Tullie</hi> ſometimes ſaid in his oration for <hi>Flaccus</hi>) the raſhneſſe of the multitude, and how the Grecian Victors handled the matter at the ſacke of <hi>Troy.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Virgil. Aen. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note>Scilicet ignis edax ſumma ad veſtigia vento</l>
               <l>Voluitur, exuperant flammae, furit aeſtus ad aras.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And then, as there <hi>Aeneas</hi> tels you,</p>
            <q>
               <l>To Iunoes Sanctuaerie</l>
               <l>Comes all the prey, and what they thither carrie,</l>
               <l>Is kept by choice men, the <hi>Phoenician,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And dire <hi>Vlyſſes.</hi> Thither the whole ſtate</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Troies</hi> wealth ſwarmes, the Gods, their Temples plate.</l>
               <l>There lies the gold in heapes, and robes of worth</l>
               <l>Snatcht from the flaming Coffers.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Or, if you will haue a more particular deſcription of the diſmall euent and bloudie effects which the vanquiſhed of all ſorts are ſure to feele, take thoſe which <hi>Caeſar</hi> reckons vp as vndoubted fruits of <hi>Catilines</hi> conſpiracie, in <hi>Saluſt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Saluſt.</note> 
               <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piuntur Virgines, &amp;c. The Virgins are rauiſhed, the children torne from their parents boſomes, the Matrons made the obiect of all the Victors luſt, the Temples and houſes ſpoiled, all things turned to burning and ſlaughter, all places ſtopt full of weapons, carcaſes, bloud, and lamentation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or if this content you not, take that of <hi>Quintilian</hi> in his eighth booke: <hi>The flames were ſpread thorow the Temples,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quint.</note> 
               <hi>a terrible cracking of falling houſes is heard, and one confuſed
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17988:16"/>ſound of a thouſand ſeuerall clamours. Some flie they know not whither: ſome ſticke faſt in the laſt embraces of their friends. The children and the women howle, and the old men (vnluckily ſpared vntill that fatall day.) Then followeth the tearing away of all the goods out of houſe and Temple, and the talke of thoſe that haue carried away one burthen, and runne for another: and the poore priſoners are driuen in chaines before their takers, and the mother endeuouring to carrie her fillie infant with her. And where the moſt gaine is, there goe the Victors together by the eares.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what need wee illuſtrate the effects of bloudie warre and victorie out of heatheniſh authors? Who hath not heard of the <hi>weeping</hi> voice of <hi>Elizeus</hi> vnto <hi>Hazael</hi> King of <hi>Syria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. King. 8.12.10.32.33.13.7.</note> the ſecond of <hi>Kings</hi> 8.12. <hi>I know the euill that thou ſhalt doe vnto the children of Iſrael: their ſtrong Cities ſhalt thou ſet on fire: their young men ſhalt thou ſlay with the ſword: thou ſhalt daſh their infants againſt the ſtones, and rent in peeces their women with childe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this, if I conceiue any thing, had beene the deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red caſe of <hi>Iudah:</hi> this (if not farre worſe) the euent of <hi>Shebna</hi> his treaſon, who all this while, as <hi>Dionyſius</hi> (of whom <hi>Tullie</hi> reports in his third booke <hi>De natura Deorum</hi>) who hauing ſpoiled the Temple of <hi>Proſerpina</hi> at <hi>Locris,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tully.</note> of <hi>Iupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> in <hi>Peloponeſus,</hi> of <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> at <hi>Epidaurus,</hi> becauſe <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerpina</hi> drowned him not as he ſailed to <hi>Syracuſa,</hi> nor yet <hi>Iupiter</hi> ſtrooke him in peeces with his thunder-bolts, nor <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> made an end of him by ſome long and miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble conſumption, thought himſelfe ſecure and paſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and that hee had done nothing but what was lawfull and warrantable, and what very well ſorted with his great ſpirit and high imagination.</p>
            <p>But beloued, I beſeech God of his infinite mercie, giue me grace, and as many as heare me this day (foraſmuch as we are all of vs in proportion of the ſame minde, wee all of vs in our iollitie thinke wee may doe what wee liſt, and ſo long as God forbeares to puniſh, we will neuer forbeare to ſinne.) But God grant, which ſhall be all the vſe I will now
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17988:16"/>make, and with which I will ſhut vp this point, God grant (I ſay) wee may remember and lay vnto our hearts what that good Father <hi>S. Auſtin</hi> ſaith: <hi>Nihil eſt infelicius:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſtin.</note> 
               <hi>Nothing is more vnfortunate then the felicitie of ſinners, whereby their pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall impunitie is nouriſhed, and their malice ſtrengthned and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed. When God ſuffereth ſinners to proſper, then his indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is the greater towards them</hi> (ſaith that Father) <hi>and when he leaueth them vnpuniſht, then he puniſheth them moſt of all.</hi> Witneſſe this ſpectacle of Gods vengeance, <hi>Shebna,</hi> who not long ſince I my ſelfe ſaw, in the courſe and paſſage of my meditations, <hi>ſtrong and in great power, ſpreading him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe like a greene bay tree: Vidi eum ſuper exaltatum,</hi> as the vulgar hath it, honoured and exalted aboue meaſure, ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uated and lifted vp <hi>farre higher then the Cedar trees of Liba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</hi> And yet now againe <hi>I paſſed by, and loe he was gone: I ſought him, but he could not be found,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 37.</note> 
               <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 37.</p>
            <p>And ſo I come to his puniſhment, which is ſet downe by our Prophet heere in ſo full and ample manner, as more cannot be ſaid. All that I ſhall need to doe, will be to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend vnto your further conſideration two ſpeciall tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and ſteps of Gods iuſtice in puniſhing <hi>Shebna:</hi> whereof the firſt is the <hi>ſuddenneſſe</hi> of it; <hi>Potentes potentèr tormenta pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientur, Wiſdome</hi> 6.7. The ſecond, the manner of it;<note place="margin">Wiſd. 6.7.</note> 
               <hi>In quo peccamus, in eodem plectimur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Touching the ſuddenneſſe of it; lend me your attention, and you ſhall finde in our Prophets commiſſion heere, what you ſhall ſeldome or neuer finde in any of the like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. All other commiſſions giuen to Prophets when they were ſent to denounce the ruine of any one man or nation, runne for the moſt part with a prouiſo, and mercie is ioined with iudgement, as <hi>Fabius</hi> with <hi>Marcellus,</hi> to temper and allay the fierceneſſe of it. <hi>Nouit enim Deus ſuas comminationes conditionaliter eſſe intelligendas, nempe niſi reſipiſcant,</hi> ſaith lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Zanchius.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zanchius de Nat. Dei. ſect. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>As <hi>Ionas</hi> the third at the fourth verſe: <hi>Yet fortie daies, and Niniue ſhall be ouerthrowne:</hi> true, if yee will not repent,<note place="margin">Ionah 3.4.</note> and amend your liues by my preaching.<note place="margin">Iſay 38.1.</note> So <hi>Iſay</hi> the 38. at the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:17988:17"/>firſt, which commination ſome thinke came iuſt at the very time of <hi>Zenacheribs</hi> fearefull expedition: <hi>Put thy houſe in order, for thou ſhalt die, and not liue:</hi> true, vnleſſe God may heare thy praiers, and ſee thy teares, and then his heart is turned within him: his repentings are rowled together, and he will not execute the fierceneſſe of his wrath, as it is <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11.<note place="margin">Hoſ. 11.9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But moſt pregnant of all other is that of God himſelfe, <hi>Ier.</hi> 18. at the 7.<note place="margin">Ierem. 18.7.</note> 
               <hi>I will ſpeake ſuddenly concerning a nation or concerning a kingdome, to plucke it vp, and to root it out, and to deſtroy it. But if this nation againſt whom I haue pronounced, turne from their wickedneſſe, I will repent of the plague that I thought to bring vpon them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay Diuines ſay, that if <hi>Iudas</hi> (whom I may tearme <hi>the Traitor</hi>) could haue repented, he might haue found mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. <hi>Iudas</hi> had time, though not grace to repent.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Shebna</hi> his caſe heere is farre more lamentable and deſperate: heere's no reſpite for repentance, no hope of mercie, all iudgement. <hi>Tranſportando tranſportabit te: Volutando volutabit te.</hi> Behold, the Lord will carry thee away, and will ſurely couer thee; hee will ſurely roll and turne thee like a ball in a large Countrey: there ſhalt thou die, and there ſhall the Chariots of thy glory ceaſe, O thou ſcandall and diſhonour of thy Lord and Maſter.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Manner. </seg>
               </label> See how euery word hath his weight, how euery ſinne beares it owne burden, and which is a ſpeciall token of Gods heauie wrath and vnpartiall proceſſe in iudgement, ſee how he meets with him in the ſame kinde.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adoni-bezek</hi> cauſed ſeuentie Kings hauing the thumbes of their hands and of their feet cut off, to gather crummes vnder his Table: and the thumbes of <hi>Adoni-bezeks</hi> hands and of his feet were cut off,<note place="margin">Iudg. 1.7.</note> 
               <hi>Iudg.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Agags</hi> ſword made women childleſſe: and his mother was hewen in peeces and made childleſſe among other women,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.33.</note> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.33.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:17988:17"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Ralphe Lardein</hi> (ſaith <hi>M. Fox</hi>) betraied <hi>George Eagles,</hi> a good and a iuſt man: and the ſame <hi>Ralphe</hi> afterward was attached himſelfe, arraigned, and hanged.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The chiefe of the Vault-pioners</hi> reſolued to blow vp the Parliament with powder: and the ſame Vault-pioners were maimed, disfigured, ſhot, wounded, and blowne vp with powder. Right ſo fareth it with <hi>Shebna. Shebna</hi> to refreſh his reputation and vphold his greatneſſe, ſuppreſſeth <hi>Elia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chim:</hi> God ſuppreſſeth <hi>Shebna,</hi> and raiſeth vp <hi>Eliachim.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shebna</hi> reſolueth to liue and die in <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> God driues him out of <hi>Ieruſalem. Shebna</hi> lookes for grace, releefe, and countenance from the enemie: the enemie diſgraceth, han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, executeth <hi>Shebna.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 83.13.14.15.17.18.</note>
               <bibl>Pſal. 83.13</bibl> 
               <hi>O my God, make them like vnto a wheele, and as the ſtubble before the winde.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 83.14</bibl> 
               <hi>Like as the fire that burneth vp the wood, and as the flame that conſumeth the mountaines.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 83.15</bibl> 
               <hi>Perſecute them euen ſo with thy tempeſt, and make them afraid with thy ſtorme.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 83.17</bibl> 
               <hi>Let them be confounded and vexed euer more and more: let them be put to ſhame and periſh.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 83.18</bibl> 
               <hi>And they ſhall know that thou whoſe name is Iehouah, art only the moſt high ouer all the earth.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Application. </seg>
               </label> And now to make ſome application, and to compare <hi>Shebna</hi> with <hi>Gowrie,</hi> and <hi>Shebnaes</hi> treaſon with the treaſon of <hi>Gowrie</hi> ſo farre as my knowledge of their like condition can parallell them together: I muſt craue leaue to flie to that old refuge, <hi>Similitudes hold not in all things.</hi> Neither ſhall I be able to parallell <hi>Gowrie</hi> with <hi>Shebna,</hi> nor his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with <hi>Shebnaes</hi> treaſon in each particular.</p>
            <p>Howſoeuer, certaine it is (to begin with that I firſt obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in <hi>Shebna</hi>) he was a man of note and eminencie, a man of maruellous comely deportment and behauiour, a man that had conquered the affections both of his owne Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:17988:18"/>and ſtrangers in ſuch ſort, as that notwithſtanding a cloud of witneſſes, the cleare and laudable depoſitions of ſundry examinants, the Act of Parliament for the forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of his eſtate, and of his heires for euer, and which is <hi>inſtar mille teſtium,</hi> the all-prouident hand of God in ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the mouth of <hi>Sprot,</hi> and hailing him to the Miniſters of iuſtice, and cauſing him to be his owne accuſer, and that an eight yeeres after, when <hi>Bour</hi> and <hi>Logan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> two other Conſpirators, were dead and putrified in their graues, and deuoured of wormes, and no mortall creature could detect him but his owne witneſſe, Iudge, and executioner, the <hi>Conſcience</hi> of his owne breaſt. Yet notwithſtanding there are not a few who ſhame not to take vp that of the Prophet: <hi>Quis credet auditui?</hi> Who will beleeue your report?</p>
            <p>But this I will boldly ſay, and it ſhall ſtand incontrole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able till the day of doome, to the eternall confuſion of <hi>Gowrie,</hi> that he was as much tied vnto his Maieſtie, as a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect in his caſe and of his qualitie could poſſibly bee vnto his Soueraigne: neither ſhall it be any amplification at all, or any the leaſt ſtraine of wit, to tell you that his Highneſſe proceeding and carriage towards <hi>Gowrie</hi> was farre more gracious and charitable then that of <hi>Ezechiah</hi> vnto <hi>Shebna.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For <hi>Shebna</hi> by the meanes of <hi>Ahaz</hi> was now thorowly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the courſe of gouernment, and happily <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiah</hi> might haue eſpeciall vſe of his aduice, and could not be without him, and that the children of God are driuen often times to relie vpon the wiſe in their generation, is not <hi>Ezechiah</hi> his caſe alone.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, <hi>Shebna</hi> (for ought we finde) during the time of <hi>Ahaz,</hi> and vntill this terrible inuaſion of <hi>Zenacherib,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in his allegeance ſound and vncorrupt: whereas <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>Gowrie, bloudie Gowrie</hi> (for I ſhall euer call him ſo: he was a man of bloud, his heart was died as red as ſcarlet with the royall bloud of an anointed King) could ſtand his Maieſtie in no ſuch ſtead. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, his race was tainted, the leauen of his fathers diſloyaltie had ſowred the whole lumpe and maſſe of his thoughts and affections, and therfore he could
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:17988:18"/>looke for no gracious aſpect from his Maieſtie, ſith of ſo bad a kinde as Traitors are, it is true the ſouldiers ſaid at the death of <hi>Maximinus</hi> ſonne, <hi>there ought not to be ſaued ſo much as a whelpe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A pardon, an indulgence, a conniuencie, doth neuer change the cankred and feſtered diſtemper of a wicked wretch. There are benefits which are odious, which exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate, and cauſe the heart of an vnthankfull malicious miſcreant to ſwell and burſt againe, when he is as it were conquered and ouercome of loue and faire vſage.</p>
            <p>All inſtances and allegations omitted whatſoeuer, take that of <hi>Parrie</hi> for a pregnant preſident, from whom in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight of <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>Deuill,</hi> the very aſpect of our late right il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Queene extorted this feruent acknowledgement: <hi>When I looked vpon her Maieſtie,</hi> ſaith hee, (and what mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell? for ſhe was the moſt glorious creature of her ſex that then breathed) <hi>&amp; remembred hir many excellencies, I was trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and yet I ſaw no remedie: for my vowes were in heauen, my letters and promiſes in earth; and had ſhe preferred me neuer ſo greatly, yet muſt my enterpriſe haue held.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what ſhould we goe further then his Maieſties owne experience? <hi>who thought by being gracious at the beginning,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> p. 31.</note> 
               <hi>to winne all mens hearts to a louing and willing obedience, but found by the contrary the diſorder of the Countrey, and the loſſe of his thankes to be all his reward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding ſo graciouſly dealt he with this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracious Traitor, that for his ſake he was content to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence with the principles of morall wiſdome, and after a ſort to offer violence to his owne princely knowledge and experience. Whereupon it was that hee heaped ſo many coales of fire vpon this bloudie <hi>Gowries</hi> head, and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all example.</p>
            <p>True it is that <hi>Saul,</hi> for reaſons beſt knowne vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, could not endure that any of his ſubiects that were diffident and doubtfull of his title, ſhould ſo much as bee called in queſtion. <hi>There ſhall not a man die this day: for to day the Lord hath ſaued Iſrael,</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.14.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 11.14.</note> And <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:17988:19"/>ſo farre foorth as it concerned his owne perſon, was well pleaſed to pardon <hi>Shimei: Thou ſhalt not die; and the King ſware vnto him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 19.23.</note> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.23.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Salomon</hi> dealt ſo mercifully with him, that he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, <hi>The thing is good: as my Lord the King hath ſaid, ſo will thy ſeruant doe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Reg. 2.38.</note> 1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 2.38. But heere his Maieſtie, vpon no one motiue in the world, neither vpon the apprehenſion of an extraordinarie bleſſing, as <hi>Saul;</hi> nor vpon a paſſion of ioy, as <hi>Dauid;</hi> nor vpon a point of policie for a ſpirt, and after three yeares to meet with him for good and all, as <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon:</hi> but freely and voluntarily, of his owne benigne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and regall clemencie, forgiueth and acquitteth <hi>Gowrie,</hi> he reſtoreth him to his land, he reſtoreth him to his digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, he nouriſheth and bringeth vp two or three of his ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, <hi>as it were in his owne boſome, by a continuall attendance vpon his deareſt bedfellow in her priuie chamber.</hi> And if all this had beene too little, he would haue giuen him (as it was ſaid to <hi>Dauid</hi>) <hi>ſuch and ſuch things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 12.18.</note> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.18.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Quorum ſi ſingula duram</l>
               <l>Flectere non poterant, potuiſſent omnia mentem.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But <hi>O ignominia domus Domini!</hi> It is more then ſtupendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to ſee how all this wholeſome nouriſhment, which ſhould haue bred good bloud, turned to venome, and how ſtrangely that which would haue diſſolued an heart of flint, and wrought remorſe, made this villaine more retchleſſe and obdurate: all this louing commemoration of ſo many binding benefits, no more mooued the bloudie butcher <hi>Alexander,</hi> then the ruthfull mone of <hi>Lycaon,</hi> fierce <hi>Achil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les:</hi> but all this he heard, and (as there the Poet ſaith) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied:</p>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">Homer. Il. φ.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</q>
            <p>For now, after a little pauſe, and conference had with his bloudie brother, he begins afreſh:</p>
            <q>
               <l>Ingreditur<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> domum, luctus comitantur euntem,</l>
               <l>Et pauor &amp; terror, trèpido<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> inſania vultu.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:17988:19"/>
            <p>Now, no one word falls from his blacke mouth, but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall death; tell not me of thy gifts, nor of thy good turnes, nor of any price of redemption whatſoeuer, <hi>die, die thou must:</hi> the death of <hi>Patr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>clus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Achilles; the death of my Father,</hi> ſaith bloudy <hi>Alexander</hi> will not ſuffer me to thinke on mercy.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Antaeus</hi>-like he renues his ſtrength,<note place="margin">Tuſc: queſt. l. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> and as a furious <hi>Rambe</hi> vpon recoyle, comes with the greater force: or as <hi>Baliſtae lapidum &amp; reliqua tormenta, telorum</hi> (as <hi>Tully</hi> ſaith) <hi>eo grauiores ictus habent, quo ſunt contenta &amp; obducta vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentius,</hi> ſo grew this bloudy <hi>Alexander</hi> more violent and outragious.</p>
            <p>Neuer did rauenous wolfe ſo inſult and prey vpon a ſilly lambe, neuer did doting ſhe-Beare rob'd of her whelps, ſo fret and foame as now this <hi>bloudy Alexander</hi> did. Where (though I confeſſe it addes little to what hath been already ſaid) yet to the diſhonor of <hi>bloudy Alexander,</hi> I beſeech you note how devoide he was of all manhood and common ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilitie. For firſt; whereas Lyons and Beares will take ſome compaſſion on a proſtrated creature, this <hi>bloudy</hi> vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine, ſhakes of nature it ſelfe and ſets vpon him as a bird in the ſnare, vpon all the diſaduantage that poſſibly may bee, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Homer: Iliad φ.</note> naked of hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met, ſhield, ſword or lance, which none but a bloudy <hi>Alexander</hi> devoide of all manhood, would euer haue done.</p>
            <p>Secondly, hee threatneth a King deſcended from as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable predeceſſors as any Prince liuing, with a reproch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and inglorious kinde of death: he muſt not die by the hands of a woman, which <hi>Abimilech</hi> held diſhonorable, <hi>Iudges</hi> 9. Nor yet by the ſword of his Page,<note place="margin">Iudges 9.54.</note> which had been a thought better, but he muſt die as a foole dieth, as <hi>an oxe goeth vnto the ſlaughter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou: 7.22.</note> 
               <hi>and as a foole goeth to the ſtocks</hi> bound hand and foote, ſo muſt he goe with all ignominie and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honor vnto his graue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It behooueth you to be bound,</hi> ſaith he;<note place="margin">2 Sam: 3.34.</note> but <hi>died Abner as a fool<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dieth?</hi> his hands were not bound nor his feete tyed in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:17988:20"/>fetters of braſſe, but as a man falleth before wicked men, ſo ſhould he haue fallen as on this day.</p>
            <p>Now let vs goe on and ſee whether <hi>bloudy Gowry</hi> came any whit ſhort of <hi>Shebna,</hi> for now all thoſe circumſtances, the end only excepted, muſt be renued againe, and brought in by way of application to aggrauate the foule inexcuſable treaſon of <hi>Gowrie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gow:</hi> conſpir: c. 3.</note> For, I will not now dallie out the time, or tyre your patience, or ſpend my breath in charging him with all thoſe ſinnes of <hi>Shebna,</hi> though I make no doubt but hee that was ſo giuen to <hi>Magique operatiue</hi> by birth and many yeeres deſcent and much practiſe, was guilty of all or more, or worſe then thoſe.</p>
            <p>Neither ſhall I be able to ſay any thing of his end, of the vltimate end which <hi>Gowrie</hi> aymed at, being as yet vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne. Howbeit that he looked no further then the life of an innocent and harmeleſſe King, or that hee proiected no other thing then the bare reuenge of his Fathers death, I for my part ſhall neuer beleeue. His trauelling beyond the ſeas, eſpecially in <hi>Italie,</hi> the mint, and; but I forbeare to ſpeake what we all know, for what haue I to doe with other nations?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gowries</hi> conſp: D. 1. col. 2.</note> Onely by the way you may remember what <hi>Rind</hi> vnder his hand ſets downe, that <hi>in thoſe parts where Gowrie was they would giue ſundry folkes Breues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His ſecret conference with <hi>Ieſuits,</hi> men by profeſſion diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers of Kings and kingdomes; men, whom that triple-crowned Monarch vſeth as the <hi>Romane Emperors</hi> thoſe they called <hi>agentes in rebus</hi> all his ſpies, intelligencers and infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, with whom an honeſt heart cannot well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, his plauſibilitie with the people, who vpon the report of <hi>Gowries</hi> death grew ſo tumultuous and ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, as that his Maieſtie was faine to cauſe the <hi>Bayliffs,</hi> and the reſt of the honeſt men of the towne to be brought into the chamber, and made eye-witneſſes of that which their hearts could not beleeue (<hi>Plauſibilitie</hi> being as you know alwaies the forerunner and harbinger of ambitious and ſwelling thoughts) theſe and the like, as the lowing of the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:17988:20"/>
               <hi>Oxen</hi> which <hi>Samuel</hi> heard, and as the bleating of the <hi>Sheep,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam: 15.14.</note> crying in mine eares, makes me more then ſuſpitious, that there was in <hi>Gowries</hi> treaſon ſomewhat that the world can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not as yet iudge of, nor the wit of man certainly determine. Wherefore, not to ſpeake of the end which <hi>Gowrie</hi> aymed at, nor yet to recommend vnto you coniectures and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions only; may it pleaſe you to remember what was ſaid touching <hi>Shebna</hi> his treaſon in regard of the <hi>Author, Obiect, Euent:</hi> all theſe preſent themſelues againe, and come (as I ſaid) by way of <hi>Application</hi> to aggrauate the fowle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable treaſon of <hi>Gowrie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, in regard of the Author. <hi>Gowrie:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gowries</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpir: D. 2. col. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Gowrie was no foole.</hi> For firſt, he layes this downe for a ground. <hi>A wiſe man intending an high and dangerous purpoſe must communicate the ſame to none but himſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">Exam: of <hi>George Spro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> pag. 41.</note> 
               <hi>Restalrig</hi> (that is to ſay a perfect <hi>Gowrie</hi>) (for they two had but one heart between them) hee calls vpon him, <hi>My Lord you must be circumſpect with your brother, that he be not raſh in any ſpeeches; ſuch a purpoſe as your Lordſhip intendeth cannot be done raſhly, but with deliberation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Lord if you will come ouer to my houſe, perſwade your ſelfe you ſhall be as ſafe and quiet here, while we haue ſetled our plot, as if you were in your owne chamber. I doubt not my Lord but all things ſhall be well.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Lord I am reſolued to perill life, lands, honor, goods, yea and the hazard of hell ſhall not frey me, though the ſcaffold were already ſet vp.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What? ſuch ſecrecies? ſuch vowes? ſuch coniurations? ſuch proteſtations? as farre as their ſoules and the damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their ſoules came to? and yet this a ſilly plot? no, no, I will graunt as much as he that is moſt incredulous ſhall or can vrge, and yet this no ſillie plot. There muſt be a <hi>concurſus fortuitorum</hi> ouer and beyond the proiect, or elſe the beſt laid plot may eaſily miſcarry. I grant it was ſence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe for <hi>Alexander</hi> to thinke that a pot of droſſe ſhould haue any adamantine vertue in it to draw bounty it ſelfe to <hi>Gowrie</hi> his houſe: I grant, it was ſenceleſſe for him to thinke
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:17988:21"/>that Curteſie or rather <hi>Glauering, bowing his head vnder his Maieſties knee</hi> could worke vpon the affection of a King, who is as an Angell of God, and can well diſtinguiſh ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance and bare complement, from truth and realtie.</p>
            <p>Moreouer; his vnmannerly importunitie, his vnſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble interrupting his Maieſtie in his game, his deiection of countenance, his deep oathes, his faultring in his ſpeech, his impatience of delay: all theſe I grant were arguments of <hi>Alexanders</hi> weakneſſe and ill managing of the plot, but the plot was ſtill the ſame and lay in <hi>Gowries</hi> breaſt, concealed and vnknowne to any, ſaue God, and the Deuill, with whom he delt, and who was his chiefe counſellor. <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> was but <hi>inſtrumentum animatum,</hi> all that hee was to act and play in this bloudy Tragedie, was to get the King to <hi>Gowries</hi> houſe, and into the chamber, and then let him and the Deuill alone.</p>
            <p>Againe, that the King ſhould vſe <hi>Alexander</hi> ſo louingly, as to lay his hand on his ſhoulder, that notwithſtanding his many coniectures he could neuer ſuſpect any harme to be intended, or that when he did ſuſpect hee ſhould preſently checke himſelfe, as being aſhamed in reſpect of the cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his owne conſcience, to giue way thereunto; theſe were not of the eſſence of the plot, neither can they be aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to any wiſdome or forecaſt in <hi>Gowrie</hi> or his brother <hi>Alexander,</hi> but to his Maieſties open ſimplicitie and harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe,<note place="margin">Chryſost.</note> there being (as Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith in his Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie <hi>de Sancta Suſanna,</hi> if the Tract be his) <hi>ſuſpiciones male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolae calumniantium &amp; ſuſpitiones beneuolae Gubernantium:</hi> malitious ſuſpitions, proper to calumniators, beneuolous and friendly ſuſpitions proper to Gouernors. <hi>If my friend betray me, I beſhrew him, but if my enemie betray me, I beſhrew my ſelfe,</hi> ſaid he.</p>
            <p>But goe we on, and follow his Maieſtie into the darke chamber of death, and then tell me if <hi>Zenacheribs</hi> armie, <hi>Rabſaches</hi> threats, the inconſtancie of the people, the diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie of <hi>Shebna,</hi> could put <hi>Ezechiah</hi> in ſuch danger, or that it was euer higher time for God to put to his helping hand
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:17988:21"/>then now? no beloued, here, <hi>here ſtand you ſtill, and behold the ſaluation of the Lord, which he ſhewed as on this day; open the booke of his workes,</hi> read the doctrine of prouidence;<note place="margin">Exod: 14.13.</note> did euer God ſhew himſelfe to bee a God almighty and a God of power, did hee euer manifeſt his particular proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence more articulatly beyond the ſtrength of reaſon and compaſſe of ſecond cauſes then now?</p>
            <p>Was it not ſtrange and miraculous, that he, that was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to bee the murtherer ſhould preſently vpon the ſight of the King (as <hi>Baltaſhar,</hi> when he ſaw <hi>the hand-writing on the wall</hi>) <hi>ſtand trembling and quaking rather like one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned then an excutioner of ſuch an enterpriſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Was it not ſtrange and miraculous that the King ſhould dragg <hi>Alexander</hi> to the window, and that his Nobles at the ſelfe ſame inſtant ſhould bee vnder that and the very ſame window?</p>
            <p>Laſtly, was it not ſtrange and miraculous that that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Angell</hi> and meſſenger of the Lord, that <hi>Ioſuah,</hi> and mighty <hi>Deliuerer,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Iohn Ramſey</hi> ſhould finde the <hi>turne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picke</hi> doore open, follow it vp to the head, enter into the chamber, reſcue the King from <hi>Alexander,</hi> and ſtrike <hi>bloudy Gowry</hi> himſelfe ſtone dead in the place?</p>
            <p>All theſe are as ſo many bookes, wherein he that runneth may read, Gods eſpeciall prouidence ouer his annoynted. Turne ouer the leafe againe.</p>
            <p>That hee that ſhould haue been the murtherer ſhould now ſtand as one that was to be murthered.</p>
            <p>That the King ſhould dragg <hi>Alexander</hi> to the window: That his traine ſhould be at that very time vnder that very window: That Sir <hi>Iohn Ramſay</hi> ſhould lite vpon that darke, vnuſed, vnknowne by-way, free him from <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> and ſtrike <hi>bloudy Gowrie</hi> dead in the very roome: read it aduiſedly, and then awake all antiquitie and ſhew mee the like inſtance of Gods eſpeciall prouidence againe.</p>
            <p>I know you will tell me of <hi>Noah</hi> in the Arke: for what in the eye of reaſon ſhould become of <hi>Noah</hi> in the Arke, in the Arke, without Anchor to ſtay her, without maſt to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:17988:22"/>poize her, without ſterne to mooue her, without Pilot to guide her, had not the ſame God, <hi>who forgets nothing that he hath made,</hi> both ſhut him in with his owne hands, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued him being in, which otherwiſe in reaſon could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue been.</p>
            <p>I know you will tell me of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> deliuerance from 70 yeers captiuitie,<note place="margin">Pſal. 126.</note> which the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, ſtrooke ſuch an amazement in them, that they were like them that dreame,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Liuius</hi> 33.</note> 
               <hi>Pſalme</hi> 126. and as <hi>Liuie</hi> ſaith in a caſe of great ioy, much liberty and freedome, <hi>Maius gaudium fuit, quàm quod vniuerſum homines caperent, vix ſatis credere ſe quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> audiuiſſe, alij alios intueri mirabundi velut ſomni vanam ſpeciem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know you will tell of <hi>Peters</hi> inlargement out of priſon, which ſo maruellouſly affected the bleſſed Apoſtle, that hee was ſcarce his owne man, <hi>hee knew not that it was true which was done by the Angell, but thought he had ſeene a viſion.</hi> Acts 12.9.<note place="margin">Acts 12.9.</note> But what was there in all theſe or any one of them, that you ſhall not read in ſome one page or other of this moſt omnipotent and all powerfull deliuerance of his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Maieſtie.<note place="margin">Reg: 12.9.</note> 
               <hi>Great is the Lord and moſt worthy to be praiſed, and his greatneſſe is incomprehenſible.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalme 145.</note> 
               <hi>Generation ſhall praiſe thy workes vnto generation, and declare thy power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> Another circumſtance followeth; In applying whereof durſt I preſume, either on the time, or your patience, or mine owne ſtrength, much might be inſerted to the indeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſhame of theſe bloudy <hi>Gowries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For they (miſcreants as they were) thirſted not after the bloud of a priuate man, nor any ſubordinate Magiſtrate, but of the King himſelfe. A <hi>King</hi> not <hi>precario,</hi> or by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt;<note place="margin">pag. 29.</note> read his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but an abſolute Monarch, and <hi>free borne King,</hi> the which with vndaunted preſence of minde he tould pale <hi>Alexander</hi> (for the <hi>righteous are as bold as a Lyon</hi>) <hi>hee was borne a free King, and ſhould die a free King.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17988:22"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A King; not offenſiue or grieuous</hi> vnto his ſubiects, but a <hi>King</hi> ſurnamed by the voice of all his people, of all humors, of all factions, of all religions, the <hi>geude King. A King, and a King of the line of Dauid, a King and a King of the tribe of Iudah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Euent. </seg>
               </label> But here I muſt lay my hand vpon my mouth, I cannot ſay what my heart conceiues, nor yet conceiue what ought and ſhould be ſaid: wherefore I come to the euent. For what of all this? <hi>a King and a free borne King, a King and a geud King, a King and a King of the line of Dauid, a King and a King of the tribe of Iudah;</hi> what of all this? It was a foule treaſon, they were bloudy villaines, what of all this? did you neuer heare of a treaſon before? did you neuer heare of a King murthered? and what a quoyle here is about one <hi>Gowrie,</hi> ſeduced happily by peſtilent firebrands abroad in <hi>Italie?</hi> or what if his deep <hi>Melancholy</hi> now brake forth and growing ſtarke mad as <hi>Aiax</hi> offended with <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>liſſes, Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memnon</hi> and <hi>Menelaus,</hi> wreckt his malice vpon a ſillie and a harmleſſe ſheepe, thinking it had been <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>liſſes;</hi> So hee, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteed of thoſe that had done him wrong (as hee thought) and proceeded againſt his Father, miſſed his ayme and fell vpon the <hi>King</hi> as vpon a ſillie and harmleſſe ſheep, who was in his minoritie, and wholy paſſiue in all that buſineſſe? why what of all this?</p>
            <p>Beloued, ſhall a <hi>Prince and a great man fall in Iſraell,</hi> the ſecond of <hi>Samuel</hi> at the third,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 3.38.</note> and will the <hi>ſonnes of Zeruiah</hi> ſtand ſtill? will no tumults, no vprores, no alteration fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low? <hi>And ſhall an abſolute Monarch,</hi> though but now in <hi>Hebron,</hi> as <hi>Dauid,</hi> yet in expectation and ſight of all the world (to the ioy and comfort of Gods Saints, to the terror and amazement of the enemies of God and his Goſpell) the puiſſant Monarch of Great BRITAINE and of all Iſrael, ſhall he I ſay, be bloudily mangled, and hewen in peeces, and no horror, no murthers, no maſſacres follow?
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:17988:23"/>Yes, yes for (to omit what thouſands <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e obſerued, ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> about that very ſame yeere, nay within the compaſſe of one moneth and weeke almoſt, many ſubiects of principall note miſcarried, and grew corrupt in their allegeance, many treacheries were attempted, many Proteſtant Princes mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſly preſerued) what meant, what meant that poſting to <hi>Rome,</hi> that gadding to <hi>Doway?</hi> what meant that hiſſing of the Bee of <hi>Aſhur?</hi> that buzzing of the flie of <hi>Aegypt?</hi> and all about this time. Whereunto tended thoſe many paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quils and pamphlets touching the doctrine of <hi>Succeſſion?</hi> Whereto tended thoſe confident predictions of the <hi>Romiſh Rabſhakehs? Nondum completa eſt iniquitas Anglorum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Pererius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dabit Deus tempus quando vetula illa anus,</hi> ſaith another, and all about this time. But of all other, whereto tended, or what conſtruction can you make of Pope <hi>Clements</hi> Bull? to wit: <hi>After the death of the Queene, whether by courſe of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or otherwiſe, whoſoeuer ſhould lay claime or title to the Crowne of England, though neuer ſo directly and neerely inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſed therein by deſcent and bloud-royall, yet vnleſſe hee were ſuch a one as would not only tolerate the Catholike Romiſh Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, but by all beſt endeuours and force promote it, they ſhould admit or receiue none to be King of England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Surely when I conſider this in mine heart, as it is <hi>Lam.</hi> 3. I reſolue <hi>it was the Lords mercy that we were not conſumed.</hi> For had not God (his vnſpeakable rich mercie be praiſed for it) vpon the deceaſe of the late euer-bleſſed Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> reſerued a ſeed, and a ſeed of a right generous kinde, for ought that we can gather from the predictions, <hi>Bulles</hi> and <hi>Briefes</hi> of thoſe <hi>Romiſh Rabſhekehs,</hi> our Land (as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſay</hi> ſaith) had lien waſte,<note place="margin">Iſai. 1.</note> our Cities had beene bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with fire, ſtrangers had deuoured our Land in our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and it would haue become deſolate as the ouerthrow of forraine enemies. Had not God reſerued a ſeed, and a ſeed of a right generous kinde, the daughter of <hi>Sion</hi> ſhould haue remained like a <hi>Cottage in a Vineyard,</hi> like a lodge in a garden of <hi>Cucumbers,</hi> and like a beſieged Citie. Had not
<pb facs="tcp:17988:23"/>God reſerued a ſeed, and a ſeed of a right generous kinde, wee had beene as <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> all in combuſtion and hurly burly: then ſhould you haue ſeene heere a <hi>Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> whipping and broiling of poore innocents, there a <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diner</hi> proſcribing, impriſoning, murdering of the right heires and zealous profeſſors of Gods truth. Then ſhould you haue ſeene the very channels in our ſtreets ſwell with the bloud of Martyrs, as <hi>Iordan</hi> in the time of harueſt,<note place="margin">Ioſuah 3.15.</note> and their bodies piled vp for fuell, for beacons and bonefires, <hi>in vſum nocturni luminis.</hi> And which is a miſerie, which the heathen, the ſublimateſt wit among the heathens could not expreſſe, no ſacking, no rifling, no razing of Cities, no bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of whole townes and villages commeth any whit neere it. Then ſhould you haue ſeene cleanneſſe of teeth in all your Cities, and ſcarceneſſe of bread in all your pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: I meane the ſpirituall famine of Gods word, when the people and ſheepe of Chriſts fold ſhould haue beene tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned out to graze on the naked paſture of an implicite faith, and ſhould neuer haue come to the ſight of that holy <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> that <hi>pabulum animae,</hi> the ſacred word of God; but hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily once in the yeere you ſhould haue had a <hi>Ducking Frier</hi> ſtep vp into this or the like holy Mount, and fed them with the <hi>ſaliua,</hi> the froth and foame of an allegoricall and tropologicall <hi>Poſtiller.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But why doe I argue the euent from the threats and Bulles and Briefes of thoſe <hi>Romiſh Rabſhakehs?</hi> or why ſhould we feare their feares, or be afraid of them?<note place="margin">Iſai. 8.12.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Who ſeeth not? nay, as <hi>S. Auſtin</hi> ſaith, ſpeaking of the bleſſings which the name of Chriſt and the Chriſtian pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion brought into the world, in his firſt booke <hi>De Ciuitate Dei,</hi> and ſixth chapter: <hi>He that ſeeth not this, is blinde:</hi>
               <note place="margin">August.</note> 
               <hi>he that ſeeth it, and praiſeth it not, is thankleſſe: he that hindereth him that praiſeth it, is mad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How that if violence had preuailed in the day of bloud, we had beene bereft of all thoſe bleſſings which his Maieſtie as a ricke of corne came laden with into this Land, euen in number as many as the benedictions of <hi>Abraham,</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb facs="tcp:17988:24"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="6 letters">
                  <desc>••••••</desc>
               </gap>dually acco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>anied his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> perſon, and depended not ſo much vpon the change of the Prince, and death of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> as vpon his and his only ſucceſſion in the Throne. I ſhall not need to rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon them; I aſſure my ſelfe there is not any thankfull heart or true Iſraelite indeed, but hath them in a table before him. Sure I am, had we wanted the leaſt of them, and had not God as on this day auenged himſelfe on <hi>bloudie Gowrie,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th ſuddenly, and in the ſame manner as it was ſaid of <hi>Shebna,</hi> we had wanted them, very babes and ſucklings would haue beene eloquent in the commemoration of them, and that now we haue them in their height and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, we are not ſenſible of them.</p>
            <p>But beloued I beſeech you in the bowels of Chriſt Ieſus, let vs in the day of wealth and all kinde of happineſſe, ſo comfort our ſelues, as that we quite forget not the day of affliction.</p>
            <p>Let vs ſo ſolace our ſelues with remembrance of what we now are, as that we abandon not all thought of what wee might haue beene, and of what God, had he not beene the more mercifull, might well haue depriued vs of. <hi>Now, O Lord God, let thy name be magnified for euer by them that ſhall ſay. The Lord of hoſts is God ouer Iudah, and let the houſe of thy ſeruant the King be eſtabliſhed before thee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Let it pleaſe thee to bleſſe the houſe of thy ſeruant, that it may continue for euer, and let the houſe of thy ſeruant and of his ſeed be bleſſed with thy beſt bleſſings. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:17988:24"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
